# Dave Cruse Elk Grove Village, IL. 60007 (224) 629-3852 crusen8@gmail.com

#### **INDUSTRIAL SALES PROFESSIONAL**

### **Profile**

Possess 20+ years of experience selling fluid power devices via distributor and factory direct channels. Manage relationships with customers ranging from small local to large national accounts, both OEM's and MRO's. Work with manufacturers to develop/enhance products for optimal performance. Support distributors and their sales staff in winning new business and rolling out new products to their customers. Assess needs, define requirements, and propose complete solutions. Highly familiar with control systems used to interface and interconnect between actuators, control devices, and sensors. Maintain an extensive knowledge base concerning product applications in a wide range of industries, including automotive, food, drug, semiconductor, printing, converting, plastics, and mobile. Willing to travel.

### **Expertise**

B2B Industrial Sales ~ Sales Management ~ Account Retention ~ Territory Development ~ Forecasting Relationship Building ~ Customer Service/Support/Advocacy ~ Client Relations ~ Communications Consultative Sales ~ Research ~ Proposal Preparation ~ Contract Negotiations ~ Follow-Up

### **Professional Experience**

Fluid-Aire Dynamics, Schaumburg, IL Sales Engineer 2017 to 2018 Oct

- Follow up on leads.
- Cold call on industrial user accounts.
- Advise customers on the most energy efficient solutions.
- Write up quotes.
- Install AMP loggers to collect data for energy evaluation.
- Coordinate installation of equipment

### A-1 Air Compressor/Atlas Copco, Addison, IL 2015 to 2017

#### Sales Manager

- Report to the VP of the Central Region, selling compressors, vacuum pumps, replacement parts, and service equipment.
- Identify customer needs and make recommendations on correct equipment choices.
- Write up quotes and follow up with customers.

# Air Services Company, Elk Grove Village, IL 2013 to 2015

### **District Sales Manager**

- Report to the VP of the Sales, selling compressors, replacement parts, and service equipment.
- Identify customer needs and make recommendations on correct equipment choices.
- Write up quotes and follow up with customers.

Combined Fluid Products Company, Lake Zurich, IL 2007 to 2013 District Sales Manager

- Operated as a distributor salesperson, managing MRO/user and OEM accounts across all of Northern Illinois, Northern Iowa, and Nebraska.
- Represented compressors and vacuum pumps from Atlas-Copco, Dekker, Thomas, Republic, and others.
- Fueled substantial growth in existing and newly discovered accounts; earned the company's top sales award as the sole salesperson to meet/exceed goals for territory sales and growth in 2012.

## CMA/Flodyne/Hydradyne, Inc., Hanover Park, IL 2003 to 2007

### **Territory Sales Manager**

- Acted as a distributor salesperson, managing accounts with OEM's of pneumatic automation, air preparation, and electronic components in Lake and McHenry counties as well as Chicago-land's northern suburbs.
- Represented Bosch/Rexroth as the main vendor and other smaller vendors to fill in gaps or achieve complete supplier ability.
- Added value to customers and significantly increased sales dollars and profitability, boosting territory sales by 20%-30% annually.
- Rebuilt relationships with dormant OEM accounts.

### Affiliated Control Equipment Company, Inc., Wood Dale, IL 2000 to 2003

### **Territory Sales Manager**

- Functioned as a distributor salesperson to manage key accounts and all MRO/user accounts in the north and northwest suburbs.
- Collaborated with factories, including VP's of Engineering and Product Development, to introduce new products into key accounts and expand market share in the territory.
- Primarily represented SMC Corporation; represented a few other major manufacturers to fill the gaps in SMC's product offerings.
- Doubled territory from \$750K to \$1.5M by leveraging experience and application knowledge to build customer credibility and loyalty, which increased account penetration and sales year over year.

### SMC of America, Inc., Aurora, IL 1998 to 2000

### **Territory Sales Manager/Distributor Coordinator**

- Served as a factory direct salesperson and distributor coordinator in the Chicago-land market, responsible for managing ten key direct accounts and supporting distribution growth in their accounts.
- Worked closely with the factory and provided samples to customers with very specific requirements; selected
  appropriate products, including industrial automation, air treatment, and control solutions, ranging from the
  smallest fittings and tubing to filtration and complete integrated electro-pneumatic automation systems.
- Arranged visits by factory engineers to develop custom product solutions.
- Rapidly increased account sales and attained a very high saturation point by applying prior field experience to earn clients' trust and business; exceeded sales growth targets in accounts every year.

### Fluid Power Engineering, Inc., Elk Grove Village, IL 1986 to 1998 Territory Sales Manager

- Represented pneumatic automation products from Wilkerson, Mac Valves, PHD Automation, Camozzi, Piab Vacuum, Bimba Manufacturing, and others.
- Supported customers in selecting and applying products ranging from air valves and associated connectors to air drying systems, including desiccant dryers and all necessary filtration and regulation devices.

- Sold actuators and assisted in designing complete automation systems; integrated digital electronics, such as serial communications and position/pressure sensors as needed.
- Co-chaired a worldwide distributor group that supported applications for mobile pneumatics in a target industry.
- Propelled an underdeveloped two-county territory from nearly \$0 to \$1.4M in annual sales, achieving substantial annual growth every year.

### **Education/Professional Development**

**Product Training** – Sprecher & Schuh, Bimba, Tolomatic Stepper and Servo Motors, PHD, SMC, Robohand, ACT CRM, Mac Valves, Summit Industrial Lubricants, TRD Cylinders, Ace Shock Absorbers, SunX Sensors, De-Sta-Co

**Selling Dynamics, LLC** – Certificate of Graduation, Sales Process Improvement (two-year program)